A Guide to the Andrew B. Davison Sermons, 1811-1847
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Andrew B. Davidson Sermons, 1811-1847
Library of Virginia
13944
.45 cubic feet
Andrew B. Davidson
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Valerie Miller, Indianapolis, Indiana, 29 June 1920.
Biographical Information
Andrew Baker Davidson was born in Botetourt County, Virginia, in 1779. He attended Liberty Hall Academy and was licensed a Presbyterian minister in 1807. Davidson served as minister at Mossy Creek Church in Augusta County, Virginia, and at Cook's Creek Church in Rockingham County, Virginia, from 1809 to 1814. He moved to Lexington, Virginia, in 1814, and served as a circuit minister for several churches in the Lexington Presbytery in Rockbridge County, Virginia. He was the occasional supply minister at Bethesda Church from 1821 to 1852. He was the stated supply minister at several churches in Rockbridge County: Oxford (1815-1842), New Monmouth (1822-1829), Kerr's Creek (1831-1849), and Collierstown (formerly Oxford) (1843-1856). He founded Kerr's Creek Church in 1822 and Warm Springs Church in Bath County, Virginia, in 1824. Davidson was moderator at stated meetings of the Lexington Presbytery in 1811, 1815, 1830, and 1836, and was secretary of the Lexington Presbytery Missionary Society in 1820. He also served as principal of the Ann Smith Academy. He married Susan Dorman of Rockbridge County 26 November 1807, and they had several children. Davidson died 7 August 1861 in Rockbridge County.
Scope and Content Information
Sermons, 1811-1847 and no date, and other speeches of the Reverend Andrew B. Davidson (1779-1861) of Lexington Virginia. Sermon topics include God's grace, Jesus' resurrection, God's government, humanity's sinfulness, and Christian morals. Collection also contains ordination sermons, including one delivered at the ordination of John P. Hudson; remarks made at the trial of Mrs. S. McClure; reasons for opposing Henry Ruffner as a professor of languages at Washington College, a review of a sermon by Ruffner, and addresses to various Bible societies, and Presbytery meetings. Some sermons contain the dates and locations of when and where they were delivered by Davidson.
Arrangement
Sermons are arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Sermon, January 1811,On the Covenant of Grace. No. 31., 27 p., 3 p. inverted and reversed, AMs. (Folder 1)
- Sermon, 19 November 1811,Jesus Christ Knocking at the Door of the Sinner's Heart. delivered at Harrisonburg, Virginia., 27 p., AMs. (Folder 1)
- Sermon, August 1814,Man's Stupidity in Destroying His Soul, Since God is Willing that He Shall Be Saved., 31 p., AMs. (Folder 1)
- Sermon, January 1815,A Call Out of Sleep. No. 42, and Wrote for a Schoolboy, a humorous speech on crying., 20 p., 7 p. inverted and reversed, AMs. (Folder 1)
- Sermon, April 1815,The Single Eye. Fragment containing dates delivered and other information, 2 leaves, AMs. (Folder 2)
- Sermon, 1815,On Hearing the Word., 32 p., AMs. (Folder 2)
- Sermon, 1815,The Moral Government of God., 41 p., AMs. (Folder 2)
- Sermon, December 1816,The Danger of Being too Much Attach [sic] to this World. No. 54., 27 p., AMs. (Folder 2)
- Sermon, November 1817,The Unprofitable Hearer. Heb. 4.4. (Folder 3)
- Sermon, December 1817,Man's Distruction [sic] of Himself., 27 p., AMs. (Folder 3)
- Sermon, February 1818,The Deluge., 25 p., AMs. (Folder 3)
- Address, 25 August 1818,An Address Delivered Before the Bible Society of Lexington at Its Second Annual Meeting, Augt. 22nd 1818 by A. B. Davidson[.] Why Stand Ye Here All the Day Idle? Christ., 21 p., AMs. (Folder 3)
- Sermon, November 1818,The Way in Which Sinners are Called to Repentance adn the Danger of Disobeying These Calls. Delivered at Lexington., 5 p., AMs. (Folder 4)
- Sermon, December 1818,Victory Over Death Thro' Our Lord Jesus Christ., 22 p., AMs. (Folder 4)
- Address, 4 June 1819,Reason for Opposing the Rev. Henry Ruffner as Professor of Languages at Washington College. Written at Spring Farm in Lexington., 17 p., AMs. (Folder 4)
- Essay, June 1822,...few years since in the Evangelical and Literary Magazine.... Preface or introduction to a book on baptism., 3 p., fragment, AMs. (Folder 4)
- Sermon, September 1822,The Folly of Bartering the Soul for the Object of This World., 5 p., AMs. (Folder 5)
- Speech, 29 August 1829,A Speech Delivered Before the Lex. Bible Society at Its Annual Meeting Augt. 22, 1829 by A. B. Davidson., 13 p., AMs. (Folder 5)
- Sermon, April 1830,The Nature and Destination of the Soul., 26 p., AMs. (Folder 5)
- Review, 25 October 1830,A Review of a Sermon Preach [sic] by Rev. H[enry] R[uffne]r in Lexington October 24th, 1830., 19 p., AMs. (Folder 5)
- Sermon, 2 April 1833,A Charge Delivered to Mr. John P. Hudson at His Ordination on the 2nd Day of April 1833-at the Lex. Church., 10 p., AMs. (Folder 6)
- Sermon, 24 August 1836,Sinners Exhorted to Return Unto Christ. A Sermon Preached at the Opening of the Presbytery of Lexington, at Its Sessions in Lewisburg [(West) Virginia], Augt. 24th 1836. By A. B. Davidson., 26 p., AMs. (Folder 6)
- Sermon, 1837,Salvation by Grace. Delivered at K[err's] C[reek]., 10 p., AMs. (Folder 6)
- Sermon, October 1838,Transgression of the Laws of God Cause of Grief., 13 p., AMs. (Folder 6)
- Sermon, 19 August 1847,The Sabbath A Sermon Delivered Before the Presbytery of Lexington by Order of That Body at Its Meeting of the Bethesda Church on the 19th Day of Augt. 1847., 14 p., AMs. (Folder 6)
- Sermon, n.d.,Prov. 29-1 A more awful reflection could not...., 3 p., AMs. (Folder 7)
- Sermon, n.d.,An Ordination Sermon. The Encouragement to Ministerial Faithfulness., 20 p., AMs. (Folder 7)
- Sermon, n.d.,Rev. III. 2. Be Watchful and Strengthen the Things Which Remain That Are Ready to Die., 4 p., AMs. (Folder 7)
- Sermon, n.d.,Acts 10.29. I Ask, Therefore, forWhat Intent Have You Sent for Me., 5 p., AMs. (Folder 7)
- Sermon, n.d.,I Have Some What Against You., 16 p., AMs. (Folder 8)
- Statement, n.d.,Remarks made in Stauton at the trial of Mrs. S. McClure., 13 p., AMs. (Folder 8)
- Resolves, n.d.,Resolved that the standing rule adopted.... Discourse against re-examination of ministers coming from other Presbyteries., 10 p., AMs. (Folder 8)
- Sermon, n.d.,Luke XI.35-Take Heed., 13 p., AMs. (Folder 8)
- Sermon, n.d.,2 Ths. 3 That the Word of the Lord May Have Free Course and Be Glorified. Outside cover says Whe the Word Has Not Free Course and Is Glorified., 24 p., AMs. (Folder 8)
- Sermon, n.d.,Ps-76-10 The Wrath of Man Shall Praise the Almighty., 3 p., AMs. (Folder 9)
- Sermon, n.d.,Thoughts on Free Communion., 13 p., AMs. (Folder 9)
- Sermon, n.d.,Another and still more awful way...., 4 p., fragment, AMs. (Folder 9)
- Sermon, n.d.,...the dreadful state into the [ ] fall...., 24 p., with 4 p. enclosure, fragment, AMs. (Folder 9)
- Sermon, n.d.,...The holy men of old rejoiced...., 26 p., fragment, AMs. (Folder 10)
- Sermon, n.d.,...if you are not going forward, you are going backward..., 1 leaf, fragment, AMs. (Folder 10)
- Sermon, n.d.,...longer, or kindred, or people might thro' him have life...., 2 p., fragment, AMs. (Folder 10)
- Sermon, n.d.,...upon the sinner,..., 16 p., fragment, AMs. (Folder 10)
- Sermon, n.d.,We all have been often called to engage in the service of the Lord. Title from last page of sermon., 10 p., fragment, AMs.